SARA NG

Department of Linguistics University of Washington sbng@uw.edu
sarablalockng.github.io

SUMMARY

I am interested in the way humans create, modify, and perceive speech sounds, especially in the way that prosodic cues to convey pragmatic and discourse meaning. My research goals are to integrate the unique information found in speech prosody into modern methods for natural language processing and understanding, and to use computational methods to aid in the linguistic study of the role of prosody in dialogue management. For example, I have used prosodic signals to recover punctuation in speech transcripts, and have used computational techniques to model speaker entrainment and conversational dynamics. I have also investigated the differential use of perceptual speech cues by listeners with hearing loss, and developed methods for identifying listener behavior in a clinical environment.

I was previously a member of the Transformation, Interpretation, and Analysis of Language (TIAL) Lab in the Department of Electrical Engineering and the Phonetics Lab in the Department of Linguistics at the University of Washington, and maintain collaboration with the Hearing Aid Laboratory at Northwestern University and CLILLAC-ARP at Université Paris Cité.

EDUCATION

2017-2024 University of Washington

Ph.D.: Linguistics, conferred 16.08.24

Thesis: Prosody in Human Communication and Machine Understanding Masters of Science: Computational Linguistics, conferred 18.08.24

General exam: Assessing the Stability of the Speech Cue Profile; Time series estimation of

utterance pitch in two-party conversation

Advised by Drs. Richard Wright and Mari Ostendorf

2013-2017 University of Utah

Honors Bachelor of Arts: Linguistics, conferred

Advisor: Dr. Abby Kaplan

Thesis: Musical Text-Setting as Evidence for Syllabification of Highly Moraic Structures in English

Bachelor of Science: Applied Mathematics, conferred

TESOL: Teaching English to Students of Other Languages Certificate, conferred

PUBLICATIONS

- prep. **Sara Ng**, Calvin Murdock, Vamsi Krishna Ithapu, Christi Miller Inferring Hearing Impairment through Dialogue Dynamics and Speech Content
- Nicolas Ballier, Léa Burin, Behnoosh Namdarzadeh, Sara Ng, Richard Wright, Jean-Baptiste Yunès
 Probing Whisper Predictions for French, English and Persian Transcriptions
 7th International Conference on Natural Language and Speech Processing (accepted)
- 2024 Sara Ng, Gina-Anne Levow, Mari Ostendorf, Richard Wright
 Investigating the Influence of Stance-Taking on Conversational Timing of Task-Oriented Speech
 INTERSPEECH
- 2024 **Sara Ng**, Valerie Freeman, Gina-Anne Levow, Mari Ostendorf, Richard Wright Effects of Information Load and Pragmatic Load on the Hypo-Hyper Continuum Fonetik 2024

- Marina Oganyan, Gina-Anne Levow, Robert Squizzero, Emily P. Ahn, Sara Ng, Ella Deaton, Richard A. Wright
 Investigating the Acoustic Fidelity of Vowels across Remote Recording Methods
 Linguistics Vanguard
- 2023 Sara Ng, Abigail Schwendiman Sleight
 Properties of Constructed Language Phonological Inventories
 University of Washington Working Papers in Linguistics
- 2022 Yeonjin Cho, **Sara Ng**, Trang Tran, Mari Ostendorf

 Leveraging Prosody for Punctuation Prediction of Spontaneous Speech

 INTERSPEECH
- 2022 Andrew Hard, Kurt Partridge, Neng Chen, Sean Augenstein, Aishanee Shah, Hyun Jin Park, Alex Park, **Sara Ng**, Jessica Nguyen, Ignacio Lopez Moreno, and others

 Production federated keyword spotting via distillation, filtering, and joint federated-centralized training

 INTERSPEECH
- 2021 Sara Ng, Gregory M. Ellis, Pamela E. Souza, Frederick J. Gallun, Richard A. Wright, Mari Ostendorf

 Assessing the stability of the spectro-temporal cue weighting angle for listener categorization

 Proceedings of Meetings on Acoustics
- 2021 Courtney Mansfield, **Sara Ng**, Gina-Anne Levow, Richard Wright, Mari Ostendorf Revisiting Parity of Human vs. Machine Conversational Speech Transcription INTERSPEECH

PRESENTATIONS

- 2021 Courtney Mansfield, **Sara Ng** Gina-Anne Levow, Mari Ostendorf, Richard Wright
 What does parity mean? A detailed comparison of ASR and human transcription errors
 Acoustical Society of America, **talk**
- 2018 Sara Ng, Joselyn Roriguez and Abby Kaplan

 Musical Evidence for Syllabification Patterns of Highly Moraic Structures in English

 Linguistic Society of America, poster
- 2017 Jenica Jessen, **Sara Ng** and Joselyn Rodriguez

 Musical Evidence for Syllabification Patterns in English

 University of Utah Student Conference in Linguistics, **talk**
- 2017 Jenica Jessen and **Sara Ng**Musical Evidence for Syllabification Patterns of Highly Moraic Structures in English
 Undergraduate Research Symposium, University of Utah, **poster**

PATENT APPLICATIONS

- 2023 Sara Ng, Melinda Anderson, Poornima Shankar, Setare Hajarolasvadi, Katherine Chase, Christi Miller Use of Biometric Signals to Personalize Audio Application No. 18 104701
- 2023 Sara Ng, Melinda Anderson, Poornima Shankar, Setare Hajarolasvadi, Katherine Chase Modifying Audio for Presentation to a User Based on a Determined Location of an Audio System Presenting the Audio Application No. 18 162847

2023 — Christi Miller, **Sara Ng**, Calvin Murdock, Nils Thomas Friti
of Lunner, William Owen Brimijoin II, Vamsi Krishna Ithapu

Estimation Of Hearing Loss of a User from Interactions with a Local Environment by the User Identified from Captured Audio and Information Describing the Local Area Application No. 18 162847

RESEARCH Positions

2023-2024	2023 UW Linguistics Fund Award; Research Assistant PI: Richard Wright	
Summer 2023	Meta Reality Labs; Research Scientist Intern Host: Christi Miller	
Summer 2022	Meta Reality Labs; Research Scientist Intern Host: Christi Miller	
2021-2022	US National Institutes of Health, grant NIH R01 DC006014; Research Assistant PI: Richard Wright	
2021-2022	Google Federated Assistant, Federated Learning; Software Engineering Intern Host: Andrew Hard	
2019-2020	US National Science Foundation, grant IIS-1617176; Research Assistant PIs: Mari Ostendorf, Richard Wright	
Summer 2019	Google Core Assistant, Pygmalion; Linguist Intern Host: Katie Vadella	
2017-2018	University of Washington Linguistics; Departmental Research Assistant PI: Sharon Hargus	

GRANTS AND AWARDS

2024	(Nominated) UW Excellence in Teaching Award
	University of Washington
2023	Excellence in Linguistic Research Graduate Fellowship
	University of Washington
2018	Travel Scholarship for Second Ethics in Natural Language Processing Workshop
	North American Chapter of the ACL
2017	Top Scholar Award
	University of Washington Graduate School
2017	UROP Small Research Grant
	University of Utah Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program
2013	President's Scholarship
	University of Utah

SERVICE

2024	Student volunteer, Northwest Linguistics Conference (NWLC)
2024	Reviewer, NWLC
2022	Peer mentor, Undergraduate seminar on graduate school application process
2021	Consultant, High school entrepreneurship competition project

2021 Editor, University of Washington Working Papers in Linguistics 2020 Student Volunteer, Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL) 2020 Organizing Committee Member, NWLC 2020 Reviewer, NWLC 2020 Proctor, North American Computational Linguistics Open Competition 2020 Consultant, Undergraduate senior capstone in speech translation 2019 President, Linguistics Society of the University of Washington (LSUW) 2019 Student Volunteer, North American Chapter of the ACL 2018 Vice President, LSUW

GRADUATE COURSEWORK

Theoretical Computational

LING 566: Syntax for Computational Linguistics	LING 532: Sociolinguistics I			
LING 567: Knowledge Engineering for NLP	LING 550: Intro. Phonetics			
LING 570: Shallow Processing Methods for NLP	LING 553: Experimental Phonetics			
LING 571: Deep Processing Methods for NLP	LING 507: Syntactic Theory I			
LING 572: Advanced Statistical NLP	LING 579: Semantic Theory II			
LING 575: NLP Ethics	LING 580: Context and Speech Variation			
LING 575: Spoken Dialogue Systems	LING 580: Experimental Phonology			
LING 575: Analyzing Neural Language Models	LING 580: Voice Quality			
LING 580: Bias in ASR				
ECE 511: Statistical Learning	GPA 3.9			
ECE 596: Conversational Systems and AI				

TEACHING

as Instructor of Record

2024 F 11	TINDS OF SULL AND A SU
2024 Fall	HNRS 217: Colloquium in Linguistics
2024 Fall	LING 311: Phonetics
2024 Fall	LING 411: Topics in Phonetics and Phonology
2023 Winter	LING 450/550: Introduction to Linguistic Phonetics
2022 Spring	LING 472: Introduction to Computational Linguistics
2020 Summer	LING 473: Basics For Computational Linguistics

Teaching Assistanceships

2020 Fall	LING 450: Introdu	ction to Linguistic Phonetics
2019 Sprin	ng CSE 472: Introduct	tion to Computational Linguistics
2018 Fall	LING 570: Shallow	Processing Techniques for Natural Language Processing
2018 Sprin	ng LING 269: Swearin	g and Taboo Language
Graderships		

2020 Winter LING 451: Phonology I 2019 Spring LING 452: Phonology II 2019 Winter LING 451: Phonology I

Curriculum Development

2019 Winter Staff assistanceship converting LING 553 (Experimental Phonetics), LING 450 (Phonetics), and ASL Program course materials to online format

Guest Lectures

2019 25 Oct LING 550 (Phonetics): Reading Spectrograms
2019 21 Aug LING 473 (Compling Basics): Formal Grammars & Parsing
2019 23 May LING 200 (Intro. Linguistics): What is Computational Linguistics?

SKILLS

Computer Languages

- Python
- R
- Matlab
- $\bullet \ HTML/CSS/JavaScript$
- Java

Machine Learning

- \bullet pytorch
- \bullet tensorflow
- Scikit-learn

Linguistic Tools

- Praat
- NLTK
- \bullet Kaldi
- Electroglottography

Natural Languages

- French (basic)
- Spanish (basic)
- Toisan Chinese (heritage)